<s3 title="Changes for &xslt4j; version 2.0.D07">
<p>&xslt4j; 2.0.D07 incorporates a <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="compat">Xalan-Java 1 compatibility jar</link>, some performance enhancements, and a number of bug fixes for bugs found in version 2.0.D06.</p>
<ul>
<li>Fixed handling of disable-output-escaping="no".  Previously, once it was turned on, it could not be turned off.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed a bug with whitespace handling where Xalan was incorrectly checking for whitespace 
    stripping before collation of multiple whitespace events into a single text node.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Whitespace stripping wasn't working with input DOMs before.  This is now fixed.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed many exception handling problems and problems with error reporting.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed a bug resetting parameters in Transformer clearParameters().<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed a bug where CDATA sections were not matching the text() node test.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Made better memory allocation problem with result tree fragments.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Made result tree fragment parsing of numbers consistent with strings.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Exceptions thrown from extensions should now be properly reported via the error listener.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed hard-coded stack dump set off by m_reportInPostExceptionFromThread variable.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed intermittent threading problem with text nodes being dropped.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problem with variable evaluation inside of union expressions.</li>
</ul>
</s3>
<s3 title="Changes for &xslt4j; version 2.0.D06">
<p>We have fixed the bugs reported in &xslt4j; 2.0.D05. Along with several other enhancements, 
we have also fixed a number of bugs found by testing and our users:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fixed some threading problems and improved support for handling Exceptions thrown in a secondary thread.<br/><br/>
Note: To support incremental output, &xslt4j; performs the transformation in a second thread while building the source tree in the main thread.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problems encountered in piping (utilizing transformation output as input for another transformation).<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed problems handling attributes and adding attributes to result tree.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Added defensive checking for null entities, null namespaces, and empty strings passed in for URIs and local names.<br/><br/></li>
<li>We now conform to the SAX convention of representing null namespaces with empty strings.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Fixed a bug encountered evaluating a variable in a predicate expression applied to child nodes.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Changed names of serializers from FormatterTo<ref>Xxx</ref> to SerializerTo<ref>Xxx</ref>. See 
<jump href="apidocs/org/apache/xalan/serialize/package-summary.html">Package org.apache.xalan.serialize</jump>.<br/><br/></li>
<li>Improved debugging support in a number of areas.</li>
</ul>
</s3>
<s3 title="Changes for &xslt4j; version 2.0.D05">
<p>All of the bugs reported in &xslt4j; 2.0.D01 have been fixed. The remainder of this section discusses two changes that we believe are of particular importance:</p>
<p><em>TrAX</em></p>
<p>The Transformation API for XML (TrAX) that &xslt4j2; implements has undergone substantial revisions since the release of &xslt4j; 2.0.D01. TrAX has joined the Java API for XML Parsing (JAXP) as part of the Sun&reg; <resource-ref idref="jsr063"/>. Accordingly, the TrAX package names have changed. The conceptual organization has also changed somewhat: The primary transformation interfaces are defined in javax.xml.transform, with concrete classes for managing stream input/output, SAX parsers and ContentHandler, and DOM parsers and DOM trees in javax.xml.transform.stream, javax.xml.transform.sax, and javax.xml.transform.dom. For more information, see <resource-ref idref="trax"/>, and review <link idref="usagepatterns">Usage Patterns</link>.</p>
<anchor name="outputprops"/><p><em>Output properties</em></p>
<p>The handling of xsl:output properties has changed: org.apache.xalan.serialize.OutputFormat and apache.xalan.templates.OutputFormatExtended were removed and replaced with org.apache.xalan.templates.OutputProperties. The SerializerFactory getSerializer() method now takes Properties rather than a String indicating the output method. You can replace <code>getSerializer("xml")</code>, for example, with <code>getSerializer(OutputProperties.getDefaultMethodProperties("xml"))</code>.</p>
<p>HTML, XML, and text xsl:output properties are specified in property files in org.apache.xalan.templates: output_html.properties, output_xml.properties, and output_text.properties.</p>
<p>You can start using the output properties defined in these files in your stylesheets. For example, you can turn URL escaping off in HTML output with<br/><code>{http\u003a//xml.apache.org/xslt}use-url-escaping=no</code><br/>
and you can control indenting with<br/>
<code>{http\u003a//xml.apache.org/xslt}indent-amount=<ref>n</ref></code></p>
<note>The colon after the "http" protocol must be escaped.</note>
<p>Character-to-entity mapping is specified in org.apache.xalan.serialize: HTMLEntities.res and XMLEntities.res. You can override entity ref 
mapping from a stylesheet. For example:</p>
<source>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
         xmlns:xalan="http://xml.apache.org/xslt" version="1.0"&gt;

  &lt;xsl:output xalan:entities="myentities.ent"/&gt;

  &lt;xsl:template match="/"&gt;
    &lt;out&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/out&gt;
  &lt;/xsl:template&gt;

&lt;/xsl:stylesheet&gt;</source>
<p>=== myentities.ent ===</p>
<source>quot 34
amp 38
lt 60
gt 62
lala 125</source>
<p>The output is:</p>
<source>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;out&gt;&amp;lala;&lt;/out&gt;</source>
<p>See also <link idref="usagepatterns" anchor="outputprops">Setting output properties in your stylesheets</link>.</p>
</s3>